Shounak Datta

Duke University Durham, North Carolina 27705 USA

email: shounak.jaduniv@gmail.com shounak.datta@duke.edu

Phone: (+1)-919-396-1988 URL: https://shounak-d.github.io/

GiтHuв: https://github.com/Shounak-D



Areas of specialization

Machine Learning * Imbalanced Classification * Missing Features * Clustering

* Deep Learning * Constrained Optimization * Multi-objective Optimization

* Evolutionary Computation

Research interests & experience

I have been working on machine learning, data mining and stochastic optimization for 7 years now. This has not only lent me insights regarding the nature of data but has also helped me clearly understand the principal data analysis mechanisms viz. classification, clustering, feature learning, dimensionality reduction, etc. and their relationships with mathematical optimization problems. I have also garnered a fair amount of knowledge regarding convex as well as non-convex optimization problems and techniques (including constrained and unconstrained evolutionary optimization and multi-objective optimization) which can be used to solve the complex optimization paradigms often posed by data analysis tasks.

My current research interests include development of learning algorithms that are resilient to the various irregularities characterizing real-world data, such as class imbalance, presence of small disjuncts within classes, missing feature values, etc. My latest project in this regard explores the potential of deep generative adversarial architectures for handling data irregularities. I am also interested in multi-objective optimization based formulations of traditional machine learning tasks to overcome the shortcomings imposed by the single-objective optimization frameworks. For instance, I have helped create a fuzzy partitional clustering algorithm, using multi-objective optimization, which can automatically determine the level of fuzziness corresponding to the data available for the task at hand.

I have supervised 20+ undergraduate and postgraduate research interns (from various notable academic institutes such as ISI, Jadavpur University, IIT Guwahati, IIIT Guwahati, IIEST, etc.) on projects leading to papers, technical reports and dissertations since 2013.

SELECTED RESEARCH PROJECTS

Some of the more interesting research projects I have worked on are:

- Deep generative network based resampling of data to tackle class imbalance in classification, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.
- Developing learning algorithms resilient to data irregularities such as class imbalance, small disjuncts, missing features, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.
- 2015-now **Developing fuzzy partitional clustering methods which can automatically determine the required level of fuzziness**, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.
- 2011-2013 **Analysis and predicting of stock market indices**, Department of Electronics and Telecommunication, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.
- Developing electrooculogram based control mechanisms for wheelchair to facilitate rehabilitation, Department of Electronics and Telecommunication jointly with the School of Bioscience and Engineering, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.

Positions held

- 2019-now Postdoctoral Associate, Duke University, Durham NC, USA.
- 2015-2019 Senior Research Fellow, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.
- 2013-2015 Junior Research Fellow, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

Education

- PH.D. in Computer Science, On the Design of Learning Systems with Resilience to Data Irregularities, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India, under the supervision of Prof. (Dr.) Swagatam Das
- M.E. in Electronics and Telecommunication Engineering (Specialization: Control Engineering), Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India. CGPA: 9.78
- B.Тесн. in Electronics and Communication Engineering, Maulana Abul Kalam Azad University of Technology, Kolkata, India. CGPA: **9.01**

Programming Languages & Tools

MATLAB coding experience for 10+ years.

Sound knowledge of Python coding using numpy, scipy, etc.

Knowledge of employing deep learning algorithms using Python, Keras and Tensorflow.

Comfortable with programming using C/C++ as required.

Extensive experience of preparing articles and presentations using LYFX.

Publications

The following is a list of my research articles including 12 journal- and 4 peer-reviewed conference-papers. For more details please visit my Google Scholar page at

https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=qtW4ugoAAAAJ

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- "Boosting with Lexicographic Programming: Addressing Class Imbalance without Cost Tuning", Shounak Datta, Sayak Nag, Swagatam Das, *IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering*.
- "Fuzzy Clustering to Identify Clusters at Different Levels of Fuzziness: An Evolutionary Multi-Objective Optimization Approach", Avisek Gupta, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics*.
- "Clustering with Missing Features: A Penalized Dissimilarity Measure based approach", Shounak Datta, Supritam Bhattacharjee, Swagatam Das, *Machine Learning*.
- "Multi-Objective Support Vector Machines: Handling Class Imbalance with Pareto Optimality", Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*.
- "Fast Automatic Estimation of the Number of Clusters from the Minimum Inter-Center Distance for Center-Based Clustering", Avisek Gupta; Shounak Datta; Swagatam Das, *Pattern Recognition Letters (Elsevier)*.
- "Handling data irregularities in classification: Foundations, trends, and future challenges", Swagatam Das, Shounak Datta, Bidyut B. Chaudhuri, *Pattern Recognition* 81, 674-693.
- "Adaptive Learning-Based k-Nearest Neighbor Classifiers With Resilience to Class Imbalance", Sankha Subhra Mullick, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*.
- "Generalized mean based back-propagation of errors for ambiguity resolution", Shounak Datta, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Swagatam Das, *Pattern Recognition Letters* 94, 22-29.
- "A Radial Boundary Intersection aided interior point method for multi-objective optimization", Shounak Datta, Abhiroop Ghosh, Krishnendu Sanyal, Swagatam Das, *Information Sciences* 377, 1-16.
- "A feature weighted penalty based dissimilarity measure for k-nearest neighbor classification with missing features", Shounak Datta, Debaleena Misra, Swagatam Das, *Pattern Recognition Letters* 80, 231-237.
- "Near-Bayesian Support Vector Machines for imbalanced data classification with equal or unequal misclassification costs", Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *Neural Networks* 70, 39-52.
- "Development strategy of eye movement controlled rehabilitation aid using Electro-oculogram", Anwesha Banerjee, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala", *International Journal of Scientific and Engineering Research* 3 (6), 1-6.

Conference articles

- "Rough-Fuzzy Collaborative Multi-level Image Thresholding: A Differential Evolution Approach", Sujoy Paul, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *MENDEL 2015, Proceedings of*, 329-341.
- "Real time electro-oculogram driven rehabilitation aid", Anwesha Banerjee, Pratyusha Das, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, Ramadoss Janarthanan, D. N. Tibarewala", *International Conference on Advances in Computing, Proceedings of the*, 435-440.
- "Single channel electrooculogram (EOG) based interface for mobility aid", Anwesha Banerjee, Sumantra Chakraborty, Pratyusha Das, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala", Intelligent Human Computer Interaction (IHCI), Proceedings of the 4th International Connference on, 1-6.
- ²⁰¹² "Electrooculogram based online control signal generation for wheelchair", Anwesha Banerjee,

Shounak Datta, Pratyusha Das, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala, Ramadoss Janarthanan, *Electronic System Design (ISED), Proceedings of the International Symposium on*, 251-255.

Theses & Dissertations

"On the Design of Learning Systems with Resilience to Data Irregularities", Shounak Datta, under the guidance of Prof. (Dr.) Swagatam Das, *Ph.D. Thesis*, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

"Analysis and prediction of time series indices obtained from stock market indices", Shounak Datta, under the guidance of Prof. (Dr.) Amit Konar, *M.E. Dissertation*, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.

PREPRINTS

2013

"Diversifying Support Vector Machines for Boosting using Kernel Perturbation: Applications to Class Imbalance and Small Disjuncts", communicated after revision to IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, Shounak Datta, Sayak Nag, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Swagatam Das, arXiv 1712.08493.

"Generative Adversarial Minority Oversampling", Sankha Subhra Mullick, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *arXiv* 1903.09730.

Unpublished manuscripts

"On the Choice of Appropriate Performance Indices for Imbalanced Data Classification: An Analysis", communicated to IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Shounak Datta, Sourish Dhekane, Swagatam Das.

Professional activities

Reviewer Duties

2018-now	ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (ACM)
2018-now	IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems
2017-now	Pattern Recognition (Elsevier)
2016-now	Information Sciences (Elsevier)
2015-now	IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems
	NI (* (TI ·)

2015-now Neurocomputing (Elsevier)

2014-now Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence (Elsevier)

Ninth International Conference on Advances in Pattern Recognition Eight International Conference on Advances in Pattern Recognition

Talks & lectures

"Data Irregularities in Pattern Classification", SSCVGIP 2018, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata.

²⁰¹⁴ "Evolutionary Algorithms", *Lectures on Bio-Inspired Computing*, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata.

Personal information $\dot{\sigma}$ contact details

Born September 03, 1989, Kolkata, India.

Nationality Indian

Languages known English (well-versed, fluent) * Bengali (mother language) * Hindi (fluent)

Extracurricular interests Painting, Calligraphy, Micrography, Graphic narratives

Residence AD-169/2, Samar De Sarani, Barowaritala, Krishnapur, 700102.